Hello, welcome everyone. It is April
28th, 2025 and we're in active model
stream 18.1 on robust decisionmaking via
free energy minimization. So, thank you
to the authors who have joined today.
looking forward to this presentation and
walk through. So thanks again and to you
all. Go for it.
Okay. Thank you Daniel. Um and thank you
for the invite for inviting us here. So
we
uh are let's say that's three of us
today. Arash unfortunately was the other
first author of the paper that made most
of the mathematics who cannot be here
today. But I will we will we will
basically go through the uh the the the
paper that we have just submitted. Uh so
let me start uh with thanking all the
co-authors. So these are the co-authors
of uh the paper that is currently on the
archive. Uh the paper provides a
computational model uh which we call
doctor free uh which relies basically on
free energy minimization for policy
computation and tries to install
robustness into decision making. So our
angle is to design policies making
decisions that are robust against
certain
ambiguities. Uh our background so from
the from the group in Salerash Jose and
myself is that of control theory. So I
apologize if sometimes maybe I would
speak about some control
terminology. So I will start with some
motivation. Um first of all motivating
the problem uh why uh we should be able
to design agents autonomous agents that
can make decision uh amid
ambiguity. uh and we will uh let's say
check some differences between what is
probably uh natural intelligent how
natural intelligence agents behave and
autonomous agents current autonomous
agents then I will jump into our
solution for free energy minimization
which is Dr. free this computational
model I'm going to talk about and then I
will let the floor to Josea for some
discussion about the code to finally
conclude with some
remarks very well so um let's start to
set out set out the ground first so um
it is undeniable that autonomous agents
have achieved groundbreaking performance
uh for the example in the figure here in
the slide on the left uh we can design
today agents embodied in robots for
example that can make very complex tasks
like building towers from blocks as the
the popular child game. Uh but if we
look closely to the picture, the agent
is performing this task in a very
controlled environment which is a lab
and perhaps the policies that the agent
learns. So the policies, the method that
the agent uses to make actions are quite
inflexible to changes against the
environment and against the task. In
contrast, natural intelligence, so for
example, a child that is playing exactly
the same game can do the same task in a
much more robust way. And this is of
course only a toy problem. Imagine what
would happen if we had these mismatches
between uh the with the environment
between the training and the environment
and what would happen if the agent
starts to misbehave. We could have
failures in the in the robot for example
that could cause damages to the
environment to the robot and maybe to
people around them. So the angle that we
are going to uh to discuss today is a is
an approach based on the free energy
minimization that tries to install
robustness into the decision making
problem. Again I speak here from the
viewpoint of a a person that comes from
control theory. Uh so we would like
really to design policies so making
decisions that allow agents to compute
optimal actions that are also robust
against certain mismatches that we will
see soon. I know this is a much broader
topic because there is a lot of research
that could feed a lot of research
programs here that spans from I don't
know m sciences designing better
actuators designing better sensors
better software etc. Here we are really
interested in the intelligent
step and in fact this is a challenge
that requires interdisciplinary
foundations and the approach that we
present is in fact interdisciplinary. It
mixes a few key ingredients of course
energy minimization
uh that will serve us as a framework to
cast policy computation as an optimal
control problem. So with optimal control
I mean the the discipline the problem of
finding optimal actions that minimize a
given cost function that formalizes the
agent task and the way we will frame the
problem we will see that this will have
a lot to do with optimization in
particular optimization in the space of
densities in the probability space which
is technically an infinite dimensional
optimization problem. So the mix of
three these three key ingredients gives
us our computational model our free
energy computational model which in fact
consists of an infinite dimensional free
energy formulation and a resolution
engine that computes the optimal policy
essentially and is able to output the
optimal policy with provable
guarantees. What is the gain uh of this
approach? First of all, um it can
provide a normative framework to equip
uh natural agents to explain uh
behaviors of natural agents. Then we
could rever try to reverse engineer if
we could distill this framework into a
robot for example as we do in the
experiments, we would be able to equip
artificial agents with robust free
energy minimization properties. And of
course coming from a rather theoretical
field like control it can provide some
elegant mathematical
methods. So the account that we use the
unifying account that we use for policy
computation is free energy. Now free
energy is very broad. Uh there is lots
of literature. It really comes pops up
everywhere in in several apparently
different domains coming from of course
neuroscience as a theory to explain
self-organization brain functions and
behaviors in general to technology tech
some technological fields such as
optimization mirror descent maximum
entropy learn statistical learning etc.
So this is really a unifying account
that we are going to leverage for
autonomous decision
making. So let's start to formalize this
decision making problem. So we are going
to have an agent uh which will embody
our model that is a free energy
minimizing agent and the agent interacts
with an environment. Now the the agent
is equipped with a model of the world a
world model which is obtained for
example from training. So this train
model we call it par bar is basically
any model of the world that the agent
has available. Now it can come from
training it can come from past
experience it can come from any sort of
different pieces of information. What is
important is that this model is
available offline to the agent and will
ground and the agent will ground its
decisions based on this model.
Now the
environment the world is as we know
nonlinear stoastic and no stationary in
general. So it is a challenge word the
one we live in and it provides to the
agent some information. This information
we call it state
x. This uh x is a label for both
observations and beliefs that are
relevant to the agent task. So x k minus
one here is the information that is
available to the agent in order to make
a decision. They can be observations and
can be belief
functions. Based on this information,
the agent well it has available the
classical generative model and it has
subject preferences that we express as
cost
functions and based on this uh as we
will see today we will be computing a
policy which is a randomized probability
functions basically probability density
function from which the agent computes
an action U. Okay. So UK is going to be
this the set of actions that are
determined by the agent and this these
actions are obtained by sampling from
the available
information. Now what is the point? The
point is that the environment the word
is different by definition from the word
model. Okay. So we would like to study
what happens when the environment
trained model differs from the real
environment. Just in terms of notation
as I said I'll try to keep the know the
mathematics at the minimum. I just like
to flag that random capital letters
means random variables lowerase letters
are just realizations and subscripts are
time dependent. Whenever you see bold it
is basically a
vector. So we have this framework here.
So we have this setup. We have an agent
that is interacting with uh the world
around
it. We have essentially a feedback
system where information in the forms of
state feeds the agent. The agent
computes an action and the actions
pushes the world to move in a new state.
So this is a back back and forth
information that we can capture
mathematically. Of course there is an
initial condition. There is an initial
state for the
environment which is a prior px0
here. Then what happens? The agent given
this initial information using the cost
function the preferences and the
generative model will determine an
action in our framework. As I just
illustrated, the action is obtained by
sampling from a policy P UK given XK
minus one. This is the policy that the
agent will use to generate UK given the
current
information
and this UK once sampled is sent to the
environment to the world and it will
make it transition to a new state
XK. Now this is just a picture a
snapshot at one time step this thing
happens this thing happens continuously
between zero and let's say some final
time n and we can capture all of these
as a product. So we have a product of
these probability density functions or
probability mass functions depending if
we are working with continuous or
discrete states. All in all, uh this big
product of probability uh mass or
density functions is just a joint a big
joint probability density or a big joint
probability mass function that in mat
lab style annotation we indicate with p
n. So this closed loop probability
function pn captures the behavior the
closed loop behavior of the agent. So it
means that captures the interactions
between the agent and the word. Now we
could do technically exactly the same
thing with the generative model. So we
could make a big product of all the the
conditional densities given some initial
prior and we can call this probability
uh function qn. So this qn is the joint
probability density function of states
and actions from the generative model.
So the subject of our of our model, the
goal of our model is that of computing
the method to generate the action. So
it's to compute the policies and the
policies are going to be computed via
free energy
minimization. So how do we cast the free
energy minimization problem? First of
all,
um we use the definition of variational
free energy. Okay, so variation of free
energy is essentially a complexity plus
an expected cost and expected loss
terms. Now complexity is statistical
complexity. It is measured using the
standard kbeck liler divergence. So the
kbec li divergence I'm sure everybody
that does active inference is familiar
with. But it has basically this
expression here. So it is not a distance
because it is not symmetric but it is
non- negative and it is zero if and only
if p and q are the same. So we have this
complexity term that quantifies how far
the closed loop system p 0n is from the
genative model. So it is a sort of an
error
term and then there is an expected loss.
Well, the expected loss is just the
expectation over the closed loop
behavior P 0N of the summation between
the state and the actual costs.
The good news uh is that we know how to
solve these uh control problems when
basically the trained model is the same
as the world model where basically you
see in green here in the slide we have p
k being the trained model and being
exactly the same as the world model. So
the good news is that we know how to
solve this uh these optimization or
optimal torque problems in a number of
of very recent papers that we got that
we got published uh and as a matter of
fact we know how to compute policies in
this setup. Let's consider one example
that we will use throughout this live
stream here which leverages a very nice
platform from Georgia Tech which is
called the robotium. The robotium is a
robotic platform that allows you to
deploy experiments remotely. So these
guys from Georgia Tech basically provide
you robots and provide you a small
workspace where you can deploy your
algorithms and they run and they run the
experiments for you.
So the robotarium uses uh a um a rover a
unicycle robot where x k the state is
the position of the robot and uk are the
input speeds at the wheels. Now in the
experiments that are also in the
preprint that is attached to this live
stream. Uh the robot has to move in an
environment that is filled with
obstacles. So whatever you see here in
reduh are obstacles and the green
position is the goal destination of the
robot. So of course we would like to
solve a navigation task where we reach
the the green position while avoiding
the
reds.
Now let's use let's minimize the free
energy pretending that the world model
and robot model are exactly the same.
But let's assume let's say that we learn
a model of the robot from a set of
corrupted data. Let's say so that there
is a very small difference between the
real model of the robot which is the one
in the bottom in blue and the the the
the model obtained from training which
is the one in red. So you see that the
the difference is only in one parameter.
Uh and the difference in that parameter
is about 10%. So as an engineer speaking
now 10% difference in in a parameter is
not that much. So it's something that
the system should be able to
tolerate. Now let's consider let's set
up the the the policy computation
framework. Let's say we have a very
simple generative model uh where the the
state distribution is a goian centered
in the goal destination and Q the policy
distribution a generative policy
distribution is just a uniform
distribution and let's say that the
preferences the cost of the agent uh
formalize collision avoidance with the
obstacles. So our cost functions are
basically something like the the one
that you see in the bottom of the
picture. So we have walls, mountains
that emulate the presence of the
obstacles and then you have a minimum in
the bottom left area in the bottom left
part of the work area minus one minus
1.5. Okay. So let's see what happens if
we pretend actually if we don't know
that the real robot is different from
the robot that we learned during
training. So let's apply the results
that are known in the literature. So we
just minimize this cost function on here
in the in the policy
space and what we see is uh something
that is quite um uh quite relevant for
us. What we see is that in this very
simple setup by using the optimal policy
and by only having a 10% discrepancy
between the real model and the model
from training basically the robot fails
in the task
in basically every time except then in
trivial situations by trivial situations
I mean situations where the shortest
path between the initial position of the
robot and the final destination is
obstacle free. You see that only in the
red um uh in the in the red curve there
is the only initial position that the
robot is able to achieve the final
destination. All the others whenever
there is an obstacle along the path so
that the robot should change direction
to avoid obstacles the uh the the robot
fails does not achieve the destination.
Of course, this means if it was a real
robot interacting in a real environment,
this means that there is a crash with a
wall or with the environment in general
that can be even
dangerous. This is exactly the type of
behavior that we would like to avoid. So
first of all, um this mismatch between
the real robot and the robot model
available during training is called
ambiguity. So we have an ambiguous model
and this ambiguity can have catastrophic
effects. So it can lead to failures that
can be catastrophic for the agent and
for the surround
surroundings. So in the next part of the
presentation and then on will follow up
with the code with implementations. We
will discuss how our model can uh
mitigate this uh this issue. So in
particular our model relies on free
energy minimization but we will see that
basically we will minimize the worst
case free energy and that means that
implies a free energy maximization step
which is quite
unusual. Then the model will allow us to
establish what are the best performance
that can be achieved by an agent that
follows the model plus will will have
some interpretability
um interpretability property. So the pol
the pro the policy can be uh the cost
driving the actions of an agent can be
inferred from the viewpoint of an
external
observer and also
clarifies some cognitive behaviors at
least hinting hints tries to explain
some cognitive behaviors in the in the
in the regimes of large and small
ambivities. So this is what the model
will do. Now let's see what the model
actually is and uh we should start by
formalizing a little bit the problem and
we should check why the robot was
failing. We should understand why the
robot was failing in the previous
example when the ambiguity was not
considered. So let's go back to our
picture. In the end what happened before
was that the real robot was different
from the robot learned during training.
So the two PDFs that were different and
this small mismatch created the crashes
that we saw in the picture just a few
minutes before we can make a step an
abstraction step and realize that we can
look at these objects in the space of
densities. Okay. Now these two objects
are just two points in the space of
densities. Let's say P bar is the
training model, the nominal model that
the agent has available and P is going
to be a different point in this space.
We are interested in protect protecting
the decisions of the agent against all
possible perturbation in this space that
are in a suitably suitably defined set.
Okay. So what we are going to define is
a is a neighborhood a sort of
neighborhood although it's not properly
mathematically a neighborhood which is
centered around the nominal model and we
are going to call this radius ea which
we call radius of ambiguity. So the set
inside the circle here is going to be
called ambiguity set and it is going to
be the radius of
ambiguity. We can formalize things a
little bit more. There are some
technicalities that I refer to the the
interested readers to the paper and we
can say that basically this set this
circle is the set of all probability
densities that have ker divergence from
the nominal model of at most ea. Okay.
Again ita is an ambiguity radius
quantifies how ambiguous the model the
training model is can be state dependent
time dependent and action dependent of
course and it has a a a straightforward
uh interpretation. Basically if it is
small for a given action state pair this
means that the agent is quite confident
or believes it is confident in the model
par in the training model. otherwise
means that it it has low confidence in
in the model that it is that it has
available. So we have formalized this.
Oh sorry there Carl maybe wanted to say
something. I I saw a hand raising.
You you did and I do want to say
something. Um, sure.
And I I I should apologize cuz I have to
go in a few minutes, but I just wanted
the opportunity to congratulate you on
on on this work. Um before I go away uh
you know there
are I think a number of things that this
work brings to the table and the first
thing I think you've really highlighted
is the intimate relationship between the
sort of biomeimetic applications and the
phenary principle and active inference
and control theoretic um approaches
which of course really start to matter
when in real world implementations and
neurobotics and the like. I I just
wanted to acknowledge that's a really
important point of convergence. Um and
just also um foreground the key advance
that you've framed and you're about I'm
going to miss my favorite part because
you're about to explain my favorite part
but uh just to sort of put it in
context. Um you know to my mind this
brings a very fresh and different view
of ambiguity to the table from the point
of view of active inference because
unlike um active inference in discrete
states space based models where
ambiguity is all about an intrinsic part
of expected free energy ambiguity in
this instance I think is much closer to
the notion that you'd find in economics
where it's not only uncertainty about
what will happen if I do this, but it's
I don't even know the game I'm playing.
Um, and this is really literally a deep
aspect of uncertainty. And basically, I
think what you're bringing to the table
here is a principled way of resolving
that or incorporating that
uncertainty, incorporating that
uncertainty quantification into a
vanilla free energy minimizing process.
Um so to my mind you know this is very
much and literally a deep solution um
that I you know one can look at in many
ways. Someone can look at this as
basically um a clever way of basian
model averaging by including uncertainty
about the very structure about the very
um parameterization of the model itself
by bringing hyper prize to the table
that say look I you know I know what to
do if this is the right model but I'm
I'll have this extra kind of ambiguity
this extra kind of uncertainty that
actually inherits from not knowing what
the model in and of itself is and you've
provided a particular structure to that.
I just want to conclude by um and this
is something that you might pick up in
later discussion. But it also um this
this sort of kind of um robust basian
model averaging or um ambig handling
ambiguity not only accommodates the
uncertainty about the very structure of
the model itself but it also resolves
something which is generic to
variational approaches which is the
overconfidence problem. Um so even if
you knew the right model the mean field
approximations that are inherent in
variational bays and you know the
minimization of variational free energy
inevitably lead to an overconfidence
uh and in principle I think the
technology you're about
to you know do a deep dive on will also
resolve that overconfidence problem
which has been longstanding um you know
in in vari ational inference and of
course really starts to bite when you
actually put robots into play. So I'll
stop there uh but just to thank you for
involving me in this work and again
congratulate you. Thank you K for the
kind words and we can follow up on the
many future and interesting directions
that come from this work that start from
this work.
Okay. So I'm going to I'm going to
continue. Uh so uh let me make a step
back maybe. Uh so let me recall here the
definition of ambiguity. Well the
mathematical details here are not that
relevant. Although the structure of this
formula is important for our proofs.
Whatever I'm going to show you is
basically proof supported. So there is
mathematics out there that supports our
claimment claims. Of course here I'm
going to keep it at a very high
level. So we want to find this policy
that is free energy minimizing but yet
it is
robust. So basically we want to find now
a policy that find a method that finds
the optimal policy minimizing the
variation of free energy but across that
ambiguity that Carl was also mentioning
just a few seconds before. And how do we
do that? So let me frame it first in
English. Okay. So again we want to frame
we want to find the optimal policy. So
we are going to find a probability
density function or a sequence of
probability density functions. Uh P star
UK given XK minus one. Now whenever you
see the star symbol means optimality and
the curly bracket over there means a
sequence possibly this is a sequence of
policies.
So we want this solution this policy to
be the solution of a problem where we
minimize the variation of the energy. So
the optimal policy is the arg is the
minimizer of a cost functional that is
complexity plus expected cost just in
the way we saw a few few a few minutes
before but the ambiguity and we must
take into account ambiguity. So we are
not just minimizing this cost functional
where we are actually accommodating for
the worst case. So we are minimizing the
maximum free energy where the maximum is
taken across all possible environments
all possible world models that belong to
the ambiguity set that I just
introduced. So we have a mean max
problem where the minimization is as
usual in the policy space but this
minimization in the policy space happens
on an inner maximization problem where
we maximize over all possible words in
the ambiguity
set. This is the let's say uh the
English translation of of of our of our
framework. We can be a little bit more
mathematical. Okay. So I'm just just
going to put the problem statement here
which looks let's say a a huge equation
but is not that complicated. So again we
want to find the optimal policy the
green the green part in the sentence and
we want to minimize the variation of
free energy which is nothing else than
complexity and expected cost where
complexity is again complexity between
the closed loop system and the
generative model and the expected cost
is specified through the through the
action and state
cost and we want to minimize the worst
case free energy across ambiguity which
means that we want to minimize the
maximum free energy across all possible
environments that belong to the
ambiguity set I just introduced. So this
is basically the formulation the
distributionally robust free energy
minimization formulation that we have in
the preprint that you see online that is
also linked to the to the live stream.
It is a challenging problem from the
mathematical viewpoint because it is
infinite dimensional and it is a mean
max optimization problem. Um and it is
also a nonlinear problem. So it is
basically we cannot rely on linearity of
the constraints or linearity of the cost
function. Actually the the big step uh
in the preprint online uh is that this
problem can be solved and this basically
gives us the resolution engine. The
resolution engine is the set the
software tools and mathematical methods
that make it possible to solve that big
optimization problem uh and make it
possible to compute effectively a
policy.
So how does it work in really a
nutshell? Um the agent which now we are
exploring so we are dealing a little bit
more details gets xk minus one the state
the current state beliefs or
observations uses the generative model
and the state cost. It will compute a
policy and the policy will be computed
by minimizing in a decursive way the
variation of free energy the max
variation of free energy. So what is the
resolution engine? What will it do? And
then will jump in the code. First of all
it can break down at a temporal scale
and at a logical level the original free
energy problem. So there are lemas out
there technicalities that tell you that
the problem can be solved at different
time steps and that minimization and
maximization have a precise order in
which they should be performed. So first
we should do maximization and then we
should do minimization. So this gives
you basically a bi level
approach and these um software and lemas
uh what they do they yield you an
explicit expression for the optimal
policy. So we know what the optimal
policy is going to be and also it tell
you what is the lowest energy that the
agent can achieve under ambiguity. So
the optimal
value from the optimal policy which is
going to be a probability density
function like the one that you see in
the picture. We are going to sample an
action with standard methods. So we are
going to sample UK send it to the
environment and the loop will continue
on and
on. So let me start giving you some just
the flavor of these key elements here.
First of all, the policy can be computed
in recursive way. In particular, it can
be shown I don't do the details here
that the policy can be computed as
straight away as a minimization problem
where the original problem is this is a
a a perturbation of the original problem
where it will be apparent that to you
that rather than the cost we had before
now we have what we call the cost of
ambiguity. We call this cost of
ambiguity because it comes from an
optimization problem. The the the the
maximization step in the in the
environment space that I mentioned
before. But this cost is there just
because there is ambiguity. If there was
no ambiguity, we would not have this
step and then we will recover classic
methods, ambiguity free methods.
So just two key takeaways here that
there is a free energy maximization
step. If you look at the top diagram top
equation top formula in green you will
realize that this is maximizing a
vational free energy. So we have a free
energy maximization step and it turns
out that this free energy maxim
maximization step that gives us a cost
of ambiguity is the guy that guarantees
robustness. Also of course as also Carl
was mentioning the model does not need
the agent to know what is the real
environment of the of the of in which
the robot is moving. For example, the
real robot mo the real real robot model.
um it only relies on the probability uh
sorry on the on the ambiguity set B
ea also in the top formula there is a C
bar that this comes from a a backward
recussion so one could use dynamic
programming or neural approximators deep
neural networks for example to estimate
these pieces of this piece I'm not going
into the details of this right
So we have two steps as we said a
breakdown a logical breakdown of the of
the decision problem. So we want to find
the policy. Finding the policy means
minimizing that cost that is now at the
center of the slide in the middle of the
slide which has the cost of ambiguity
and this cost of ambiguity comes from
maximizing the free
energy in order to make the model
useful. So deployable essentially we
need to find a way to compute the cost
that cost of ambivity cost of ambiguity
that I remind you comes from this
optimization problem now this is a very
hard optimization problem because it is
infinite dimensional so this is
optimization in the space of that bit
okay and it is also a nonlinear problem
although in a constraint that is a
compact set it turns out that most of
our methods the formal methods that we
developed were aimed at proving that you
can actually compute this cost in a
rather uh efficient way abat or at least
with uh offtheshelf tools from convex
optimization.
Okay, I this is actually a set of
theorems propositions and lema which I'm
going to package as a meta theorem which
is very informally stated. This meta
theorem says that the cost of ambiguity
uh has a specific form. It's EA plus C
tilda. Okay. Well, EA is a given. EA is
the radius of ambiguity and C is what
our model computes. Now this C tilda
comes from solving an optimization
problem that now is a scalar
optimization problem. So in this formula
alpha is a non- negative scalar value.
So we just have scalar optimization and
bet the alpha is a function that I'm not
going to specify here but it is
convex. So in the end we can reccast the
problem of solving of finding the cost
of ambiguity and address this problem
via a convex scalar optimization problem
that moreover has a global minimum of
course because it is convex
optimization. So we can go back to our
resolution engine and say that that
general step about uh finding the
maximum free energy can be addressed
with a scalar convex optimization
problem. So we did not build a solver
for this. We used offtheshelf
tool. So that the problem that we are
going to minimize now the cost
functional that we are going to minimize
has a very specific structure. You see
that the cost of ambiguity is EA plus c.
So the only thing that is needed to be
to be done is to minimize this guy in
the space of
policies. Now this might oh sorry I
forgot. So what what is the the the the
engine actually doing? Taking the
generative model it is computing a cost
of ambiguity which many sometimes it has
this double shaped potential here. So
this is a cost of ambiguity means that
in minus one and one the ambiguity is
very low or or it is lower than other
parts. Uh and for
example towards the end of this diagram
towards the size of this diagram the
ambiguity is much larger. So the cost is
much much larger. So what does our model
do computes this cost of ambiguity and
will output the policy and the policy
comes from minimizing this cost
functional here. Now this might seem as
a very abstract um as a rather abstract
um problem optimization problem but
actually it is very popular in the
literature and it even has a a policy
that has a well- definfined algebraic
solution which is a softmax. So what you
see here is basically a softmax function
a twisted softmax
function and what what what is the idea
uh that this formula that this policy
implements? Well, the the the optimal
policy expression is telling us that the
optimal solution is given by the
generative model Q. So the the bias of
the agent, the the the beliefs of the
agent in a sense and this model is
somehow weighted and or distorted by an
exponential. Now the exponential um and
what I think it is quite interesting is
that the exponential assigns lower
values that are associated to high
ambiguity. So in the end the probability
of getting an action that is very
ambiguous is going to be lower and lower
according to our model.
Moreover, as I said before, we can also
quantify what is the smallest possible
free energy which has a log sum x
expression which is standard in the
literature from physics for example. So
there is quite a lot on this slide. So
I'd like to emphasize again the optimal
policy the structure the optimal policy
is nothing else than a twisted or
distorted version of the generative
model Q UK given XK minus one and
distortion happens to an exponential
function and the exponential is lower
when the ambiguity is large. So this
means that the probability of sampling
an action that is that is associated to
high ambiguity is very small.
So the policy in our model has a very
clear and neat structure at least the
algebraic structure. What happens inside
the model? So we can continue developing
the flow of information inside the
model. So we have the cost of ambiguity
computed with that scalar optimization
problem. We gather the generative model
and we build the exponential inside the
policy formula. Then the two terms here
are multiplied with each other and after
normalization we obtain the policy. You
see it is quite clear that the policy
the optimal policy coming from
multiplication and normalization is a
compromise between the generative model
and the ambiguity.
So let me close the loop going back to
the uh original problem that I was
considering where the classical method
would fail in this setting. So we have
our rover unicycle robot that is moving
in this environment filled with
obstacles. We have the same generative
model as before, the same training and
robot model as before and the same cost.
So exactly the same frame.
And I remind you that when we don't take
into account ambiguity, bad things can
happen in the sense that the robot can
crash in the obstacles unless this is
really unless we really have a trivial
situation. With our model instead with
Dr. 3 starting exactly from the same
initial conditions and starting with
exactly the same setup, you see that the
robot is able to be to navigate towards
the destination. So for example, take
the green the green trajectory the green
path of the robot in the right side of
the slide on the right side of the slide
it will crash in the obstacle in the
bottom obstacle. Instead in the left
with our model in the left part of the
slide with our model it is able to
reroute in order to achieve the
destination and reach the the final
destination.
Now uh I think I gave uh quite a few
details uh and um probably the best
thing is to jump to the code to see it
in action unless there are questions or
or comments that you would like to
discuss at this stage.
Looks awesome. Please continue
then. Please I like to share the screen.
Okay.
Uh please confirm. Can you see my
screen? Looks good. Thank you. Okay. Uh
hello everyone. My name is Josepha and
I'm a postoc with Javanni at University
of Salerno and my background is in
control theory. Uh I would like to thank
Daniel for inviting us for this
presentation and I will present the uh
code walk through for the robust
decision
making free energy
minimization. So uh we will start with
uh we start with the out uh first we'll
start with the resolution engine
uh then we'll discuss the robot
experiments in more detail. What is the
cost structure for this uh uh
implementation? How we train the
dynamics model? How we define the cost
function? Uh what is the ambiguity
radius and what is the cost of
ambiguity? How is computed and at the
end how we compute the policy basically
and then we'll talk about the incilico
and experimental results and then I will
talk about in the end about the belief
of that part which is a very cool part
for of this Dr. free
algorithm. Okay. So the resolution
engine as uh Joanni just presented a few
minutes ago uh we uh uh we want to solve
a problem in which uh we want to obtain
optimal policy a set of optimal policies
uh which minimizes the maximum uh free
energy uh cost basically and we have the
uh we have our model the environment
environments model the real the real
environments model is inside a ball
centered around a nominal uh model P bar
and in the code I call P bar as a
nominal
model and uh so we we decompose this
problem into a B level problem where we
want to minimize over the free energy
and the the maximum maximization of the
free energy is implicitly incorporated
in the terms of EA and CLI that which
which makes the cost of ambiguity and we
obtain by solving this problem we obtain
the twisting kernel policy where
uh EA and C tilda are the exponent of
your exponential policy. Um so this is
the flow of the Dr. free resolution
engine.
Now, so first I will introduce the robot
experiments that uh we want we use the
robotium platform by Georgia Tech. Uh
and you can send your code to them and
they will implement your code on the
robots and you can they they will send
you the video and the results basically.
And what this is a real real snapshot of
the platform of the work area and the
robot a unicycle robot basically what
what we want what our task is that uh we
want to drive the robot successfully to
the cross uh while avoiding the red
obstacles. Basically
uh the work area is around uh 3 cross 2
m in
size and uh there are multiple robots if
if you have multi- aent problem also
it's a it's a good platform for for but
for now we only consider a single agent
here for
simplicity. Um so this is what the code
looks like. uh um so first we we define
the global variables and action space
um so so we import all the necessary
libraries here the RPS is the robotarium
python simulator uh it's a package by
the robotarium platform uh and we call
the robotarium which initializes a robot
the transformation from the unicycle
dynamics to the to the linear dynamics
and all the Other utilities we call um
to solve the optimization problem for
obtaining the cost of ambiguity we use
scypi
uh and it's a minimize tool uh tool to
to minimize the function and uh we use
some other plotting functions uh
plotting libraries like math math plot
lib and skarn to initialize our question
process model. Um here uh I define the
action spaces. So action spaces is
basically the velocities of the robot in
both axis x axis and y axis and we
define it as a grid of a 5 + 5 uh uh
discretization and it ranges from 0us
0.5 to 0.5 the speeds of the of the
robots in both directions.
Um now uh after uh doing this uh first
uh what we have to do is to load the
dynamics model or train the dynamics
model. So the p bar is the model that we
have from the of the environment learn
by some set of data. Um and here in our
case we have three different data sets.
X1, X2 and X3 are the like the states of
the robot uh at the positions and the U1
the U is the input or the velocity is
given to that robot at particular time
and uh we create a stack of these two to
make the training input and y is our
target. So the next possible state given
the previous state and the current input
what will be the next state is uh is
represented by y. So we have such three
data sets each consisting of 500 samples
and uh we train three different gshian
process models uh here and the
uh so the gshian process basically the
main the most important component of a
gshion process model is the kernel
function. So the kernel function is
basically uh finding the diff the
distance between the two data points at
a given time.
So here uh the the most uh widely used
kernel function in a in a gshion in a
gshion process modeling is a RBF kernel
with some constant term added multiplied
to it. So here we define the kernel
function uh the co the the
the constant term the RBF the RBF uh the
the radial basis function has a
parameters called length scale and since
we have a fourdimensional input we have
four dimensional lens scale parameter
which is this is lens scale is
hyperparameter I'm just initializing it
here uh plus some white noise because
white noise because your data collection
channel can be noisy And so to model
that noise, we have a white kernel uh
function as well here in the in the
entire kernel function. Uh now given
this kernel function, we initialize the
regression process regressor and um we
take this regressor and we start the
fitting uh and we use the fit command
basically uh for this and uh we obtain.
So this is the kernel parameters and
what we want to what after training what
we obtain is the hyperparameters of
these kernels. So the the the sigma f
here is the constant kernel uh
coefficient the the rbf here the rad
basis function here has a parameter w or
the length scale uh we we have that
length scale here and the noise term
here. So these are the results of the
three different data sets uh for the
three different gshian models. Now we
take this uh models
and then we move on to defining our cost
function for the expected loss here. So
the loss function is basically
consisting of three terms. So the first
term in the cost is a squared distance
between the goal point and the state. Uh
the second term the cost sum actually is
a RBF kernel again centered around the
obstacles. So here uh are the location
of the obstacles on the work area of the
robotarium and we we calculate the RBF
kernels. we center the RBF kernel around
these blue points and
uh we get the go sum. So basically what
it's doing is that when you are near an
obstacle the go sum the second term will
have a very high value so it will shoot
up uh and the third term which with a
coefficient five here is for the walls.
So we don't want our robot to go outside
the outside the work area. So we don't
want to get it outside the this
rectangle. So basically it's like a it's
like a control barrier function when uh
if it's near the wall
uh this fun this term has a very sharp
rise uh and the cost is very high. So
this is this uh this summarizes our cost
function. And so the cost function takes
uh the the initial state uh as an input
and the goal points where you want to go
the robot wants to go and the obstacle
points uh as as an input and gives out a
uh a scalar
cost. So this is what uh when we compute
this state cost this function for the
entire grid this is what our function
looks like. So you can see that you have
a very high value when you're far from
the goal and you have very high value
near the obstacles and around the around
the boundaries and you have the lowest
value near the bottom left uh where the
goal is in our
scenario. Uh so we take this uh cost
function and the and the gshian process
model and
uh um now we come to a very important
part of the resolution engine is the
cost of ambiguity. So the cost of
ambiguity as discussed before depends on
the two uh two terms which is EA and
cilda. The EA is the ambiguity radius
and the CTa is the uh is a cost
transformed cost uh which uh is the we
define like this. So the cinda function
takes an array of costs uh from the cost
function. EA the ambiguity radius. Uh
here the P bar is the nominal model
probability function and the generative
I I call the generative model the Q in
the paper as a reference problem and it
gives out the scalar again uh in the
cost in the form of transform cost. So
uh before Joani introduced a a term in
the C tilda computation V alpha uh this
objective function is the V alpha. So
this is the objective function that we
want to minimize basically and it
depends on the in the parameter alpha
and it consists of two terms. First is a
fine term in alpha. So alpha into the
ambiguity raises ea and the term two
basically is alpha into the log some
exponential
uh of the of the
cost with raised to 1 by alpha. So we
want to minimize this objective function
over alpha. Uh we take the minimize the
minimum value of this objective function
and we we basically compare it against
the baseline which is computed by the
maximization of this uh log x of the
cost and the minimum value gives you c
tilda.
uh for for more more detail I uh you can
refer to the to the paper uh how it is
formalized there. So this minimization
gives you the cilda uh which is
dependent on EA and
alpha. So EA here uh we define EA as a
scale divergence between the uh the goal
points and the next possible state
computed from the caution process
model and for computational stability we
clip it between 0 and 100. Uh so K level
is basically the the diff the the
distance between it's not a distance but
it's a it's a difference between the
two different distributions P and Q and
oh here I made a mistake I think there
should be Q here instead of P. So this
is the expression for K divergence and
for the
gshian distributions you can compute the
scale divergence in an analytical form
in a closed form without any sampling.
So now uh given EA and C tilda
uh we can compute our policy which are
EA and C
tilda makes
the makes the exponent of our policy. So
the policy here the P star the optimal
policy is a is a twisting kernel where
uh uh the q is the generative models
policy and the exponential in
exponential is uh the gives you high
value if the c tilda the ambiguity cost
is low.
uh in this case particular case in this
example we consider q to be uniform and
since it is uniform you can basically
uh remove it from this expression of the
policy. So the policy computation code
uh
starts uh the policy computation code uh
takes the initial state
uh your control space because we have
two inputs. You have two spaces the
control or action spaces uh the world
points and the obstacle points and gives
out a
uh in this case it will give out a 5 + 5
matrix of a probability uh uh it's a
probability function from which you can
also sample the action that you that
that will go to the to the
agent. Um so for this computation first
we initialize the exponent inside the
exponential
uh with the control space according to
the control space and we also initialize
the the the policy uh distribution
according to control space size. And now
we we go we compute using the for loops
for each possible combination of action.
We take the combination of that action
we give this action to the gshian
process model and we compute uh we
predict the next state the next possible
state and uh the gshian process model
will give you basically a mean and a
coariance. So the here the next nominal
is the mean of the goian process and the
sigma norm is the is the coariance and
using this uh we compute the
samples the we sample from this uh mean
and coariance uh the next possible
states and using this sample
um we we compute the we compute the cost
uh sample the costs for this number of
samples. So
here okay. So now after after computing
the samples I compute the EA the
ambiguity radius again the ambiguity
radius uh as mentioned before is a kale
divergence and it is clipped between 0
and 100 and uh I take the number of
samples 100 number of samples and I
compute the cost for uh all the next
possible states uh and I give this cost
matrix and the EA to the CTLA function
and as uh I showed earlier uh it will
give out give out another scalar value
the transformed cost which is our this
is our exponent the minus the minus
tilda is our
exponent and uh so here we use a
exponential trick to to normalize this
uh and formulate the action PDF because
uh to avoid any overflow and underflow
we subtract the exponent with the
maximum of that exponent matrix
And basically you have
the you have you have the normalized uh
PDF here and we we do the flat
flattening operation and unraveling the
index and then we take the sample the
action from that
uh from this PDF and we give the action
the the the agent will then give the
action to the state uh to the
system. So uh given this uh uh policy
uh code now we we want to apply to the
robotarium uh example and we perform uh
basically
uh 12 set of experiments on three
different training stages. So the doc
you can see in the top panel on the top
is the doctor free algorithm and the on
the bottom is the aware uh panel uh
where you can see that the the doctor
free agent even with unknown
uh unknown system dynamics it can still
reach the goal without uh uh colliding
with any obstacles while the ambiguity
unaware agent although the policy it is
computing is also So um
optimal it uh it encounters or collides
inside the obstacle only in some cases
when you can see that the obstacles are
not present in the way of the agent it
will reach the goal. So uh this is we we
show that uh how our method uh basically
solves the issue of uh uh the the model
mismatch and we also have the
experimental results for this. So you
can see the agent uh the robot moving in
the environment the actual robot and how
it uh avoids the
obstacle. So because of some uncertainty
sometimes the robot also uh gets a bit
confused let's
say but but uh anyway it will it will
reach
the the destination without uh without
colliding which is uh quite cool.
Okay. Yeah, it's uh it gets Okay. Could
you just share a little bit? Could you
just share a little bit right there?
What what is its spatial awareness like?
Is it aware of its coordinates? Is it
have a egocentric or alocentric
navigation? Like how does it understand
the location and the relative position
of the obstacles? So, so, so the so
yeah. Okay.
Uh so uh here in this case um so the the
the location is provided by the the
camera. So the camera is tracking the
top camera is tracking the robot and it
it updates his location. The camera
computes his location and updates the
location on the on the grid.
Also it it uh here it uh it has the
input. It it knows the obstacles
location. So it is pre pre is given in
the cost function we define the obstacle
points. So it knows the obstacles are
are present. So when it comes near the
obstacle the cost function is
automatically very high and it's it
avoids immediately the
obstacle. I hope uh it answers your
question. Okay. So it it's aware of its
two-dimensional position and of the
obstacle and the goals and it computes
kind of like a suitability that's
ambiguity aware. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Awesome. Thank you. But uh but it's but
the but the thing it does not know is if
it takes this action. So if it takes
let's say from the grid uh from the
action space it takes uh one action. It
does not know it. It it it does not know
where it will take this action will take
it. So it cannot foresee accurately
where this action will take it. So
that's where the ambiguity parts come.
So that's where the ambiguity is. So it
does not know exactly cannot be sure of
its own decision.
I I'll just ask one more. Oh yeah,
please go ahead. Yeah. Okay. No, no,
please ask. Yeah, I'll ask one more
question from the live chat. So Andrew
Pasha wrote, "I'm wondering about what
degree of computational overhead this
computing the worst case ambiguity adds
to running the agents." So like just in
this situation, what was kind of the
computational complexity or the resource
use of these different stages of the
algorithm? like does the Dr. Free add a
small overhead to uh most of the
computational cost being on the policy
inference or does this ambiguity add a
significant computational overhead?
Uh no uh it's uh for sure because of the
com uh because of the ambiguity uh
computation of the ambiguity uh cost
there is a there it is a bit slower than
the the ambiguity another agent but as
you can see uh here in the sorry in the
video
uh it is all real time so it is doing
the it is calculating the actions uh in
real
time uh I don't know the video is gone
for some reason. Okay. Ah yeah if I if
if I may add something uh Daniel I think
this is an excellent question because it
may be a a a research research program
per se. So finding the computational
tricks that
uh improve uh improve computational
efficiency as much as possible. Yeah. So
there are many tricks indeed.
Yeah. So the one thing that uh would be
interesting to see is because I can if
if you allow me to go back a little
bit. Okay. So policy computation here
you can see that we are looping over all
the possible actions here. But you don't
need to do that. You can have a
multi-threading or some parallel
computation and you can compute all the
actions for sorry the computation the
cost for all the possible actions in a
parallel computation and which will
which will uh which will uh I think make
it much more faster because here we are
using the for loop over uh the it's uh
so it's it has a if the if the action
space is very large then it will for
sure have a very uh high computational
overhead. Right. But you can uh I think
you can you can resolve it by parallel
computation in the in for these four
loops. Okay. If uh there are no more
questions uh I will go
ahead. Okay. So uh now we'll come to the
belief update part. So belief update
what is belief update is that
um that uh if agent is performing some
task we can learn the objective
functions of the agent of the expert
agent just by their data of the input
and the states data of that agent and uh
uh the cool part for the doctor free
policy computation is that the
policy is very interpretable. So you can
reconstruct the objective function of
the agent
uh simply by using the data the state
and the input data of the expert
agent and we do this by by solving this
uh by minimizing the likelihood negative
likelihood
uh given here. So the the likelihood
function is basically a summation of the
aine term plus a log sum x and because
both of the both of the terms the aine
term and the log sum x are convex this
optimization problem is convex even
though the the cost function uh or the
objective function
uh of the expert agent is non-convex in
nature. So the major the major
components of for this uh belief update
are the features the cost features and
the weights the feature weights. The
feature weights is the thing that we
want to learn by optimizing over the the
lock likel
function and uh so first uh let's see
the code structure for this to solve
this problem. So again we define the
global variables the action space we
have to load the the train models uh for
and the expert agents data. So we have
the data of the state and the action for
from some expert. Uh we define the cost
features. Uh we compute the feature
expectations
uh using the gshian process model and we
formulate and solve this optimization
problem here and we obtain the recon
reconstructed cost.
So, so I will start with the cost
features here. What what is the cost
features that we define? So, similar to
the previous uh task, I am defining the
cost feature as
the as the three as the two terms. The
first is the the square distance from
the goal point and the second term is
again the gshian or the RBF kernel
centered around some points and the RBF
kernel is defined uh by this function
here. Um so the RBF kernel now is not
defined only on the
obstacles the the actual obstacle in the
environment but now the the RBF kernel
is defined on a set of uniformly
distributed points on the grid which may
or may not represent the actual
obstacles. So you can see that this is
the the the feature the feature map or
the feature uh grid and this is
uniformly distributed and the actual uh
actual obstacles are here and
here. So we the so the algorithm has to
learn how to how to give importance to
the relevant features only and not to
random features in the in the
environment.
Okay. So given this cost features uh we
solve this minimization
problem and
u so we have let's say we have m number
of samples from the expert agent. So we
initialize the initial state and the uh
and the the
features. So for again for all the
possible number of inputs we compute the
next possible state using the uh gshian
process model. And we sample a number of
samples from from this question process
model and we compute the
features and uh we compute these
features uh and we basically do the
averaging or the
uh we do the we do the averaging and we
compute the expected value for these
features. So here the first the second
term uh of the uh of the equation was
lock some exponential and for that you
need to compute the features for all the
possible inputs while the first term of
the of the likelihood function was an
aine term which only computes the given
action taken from the expert agent. So
you can see here at the end there are
two terms. The first is the fine term in
the W uh which which takes the feature
sample which is dependent only on the
input given from the agent.
uh while the log sum exponential uh is
depending on all the possible inputs uh
the feature computation for all the
possible inputs and taking these two
terms we stack for the entire uh time
horizon m capital m and then we minimize
it for the summation of this entire
trajectory time trajectory. uh since it
is a convex problem um you will have an
optimal solution for any initialization
of the weights. So for this pro for this
problem particular problem uh we get
this set of weights and you can see that
the where there was obstacles in the
grid in the in the center you have very
high weights while all the other weights
are near zero or are very low compared
to the the the real obstacles. So, so
this was the real cost function or
objective function of the expert agent
and this is the reconstructed cost
function of the obstacle of the of the
uh agent and you can see that they are
very similar in nature. So you have high
cost away from the from the goal point
and you have uh the obstacle in the
center uh so on so forth and using this
cost function the the reconstructed cost
function the agent is still able to go
to the goal while avoiding the
obstacles. So just to recap, so the core
structure for the robot routing task was
to have the define the global variables,
action space, load and train the
dynamics
model cost function and the features,
compute the policy uh and you compute
the the collect the data and basically
visualize uh the robot uh uh going to
the goal. While in the bic of that code
structure, we also define the glo
global. We define the cost features.
Hello. Yeah, go ahead. It just blipped
for a second. You're back though. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Sorry. Uh so, okay. Um
as I was saying so the belief update
structure uh we also need to define
global variables and action space. Uh we
need to load the trained models. We
define the cost features um and uh we
compute the feature expectations and we
formulate and solve the uh minimization
of the log likelihood function and we
obtain the reconstructed cost. So yeah.
Okay. Uh okay. If you have any questions
uh now I'm happy to take them. Awesome.
Yeah, I'll ask a few uh quick questions
and if anyone else has a question in the
live chat, go for it. So, first just uh
it was mentioned that it's infinite
dimensional. So, could you unpack what
that means as you're dealing with a
finite number of dimensions in terms of
sensors and actuators? So, what does
that mean for it to be infinite
dimensional?
Okay. Ah the the infinite dimensional
was actually here. So uh it's regarding
to
the maybe professor slide is better for
this. I can uh maybe maybe I can put my
slides because this point is more clear.
Okay. Give me just one split second
please.
So to answer your question Daniel uh so
do you think that infinite dimensional
nature comes from the from the statement
of the problem? So the so you are not
you are not sharing I I I see it
actually I see it. Ah okay. So
maybe I'm not sure it's like on on Zoom
like select maybe you're both sharing or
something.
Oh okay. But it's good though. I I see
your I see your slides. You see it.
Okay. Perfect. Okay, the infinite
dimensional that that was mentioned
before is in the mathematics in the
formal aspect of the uh of the framework
because this optimization problem is uh
has as decision variables the functions.
Okay. And that makes it an infinity
dimensional optimization. U when
engineered uh Dr. Free on the code of
course you need to estimate this
function. So he made a step that
discretizes at some point some of these
functions uh and that of course reduces
the problem to the uh
finite dimensional optimization. So the
infinite dimensional
uh feature that uh we were referring to
was about the the problem statement. So
the fact that we are optimizing in
functional spaces.
Awesome. Okay. Another question like how
would someone go about adapting this to
another
setting? Like how would they think about
framing the kinds of uh algorithms and
approaches that are already in the
active inference or the cybernetics
literature? Where where do you see
opportunities like which systems for
applying this? And then how adaptable or
how would you go about adapting the
open- source code you've provided to
give this sort of ambiguity aware
overlay?
So I'll go maybe with the framework and
then I'll let Josea comment more on the
code since he developed the code. Um so
uh well the framework is uh I would say
rather general. Um so the I would say
that the system level steps would be to
identify a good cost functional uh
identify the ambiguity set model the
environment uh the training model and
and everything else that comes with it.
Once you have this key and and the
generative model of course once you have
these key ingredients I see um this
framework fitting in the context of
sequential policy optimization which is
really sits is the bread and butter of
control theory but also cybernetics and
it has a lot of interdisciplinary links
with with signal processing etc. In
terms of code, I think I will let those
have a answer that. But the main
challenge is going to be the computation
of the integrals and the uh uh pre
probability density functions that are
implied by the uh by the framework.
Okay. Yeah. Uh so interesting question.
Uh so there are uh I think robotics is
one of the fields in sequential decision
making which is very very cool to apply
this because we have seen that when you
have a mismatch in parameters of the
models of the system uh the robotics uh
the the task is very difficult to
perform. We also also seen robots fail
when they mismatch in the in the
parameters. Um so if somebody wants to
apply or implement this framework
uh uh I would think that the they would
first need to change the the the
dynamics model that they have. So you
need to adapt your dynamics model
according to the system that you have
first first of all.
Um then uh for example if uh if you are
in working in environment in which uh
the how can I say the nominal model and
the generative model are not really
gshian that at that point you will not
have the analytical solution or the
close form solutions as given in the
code and for that I think you need to
revert to sampling some form some form
of sampling to compute the integrals and
the expectations. So that's one part
that uh I think if uh if someone wants
to implement this on a in a system which
is more complicated and doesn't have
gshians assumptions then yeah you need
to you need to consider sampling.
Uh another part would be as I said if
the action space of
the of the of the system is too large
then to avoid operational overhead you
need to consider parallel computing
maybe or some form of vectorization to
to avoid the for loops in the
input. Um yeah that's that's that's I
think that's the that's the core path
but other things like the cost of
ambiguity the function that the function
that computes this cost of ambiguity the
structure would be the same for
that. Yeah. Awesome. So, sort of in
closing, what are your next steps for
research or h how do you see this
continuing or what ways would you like
to see people in the community kind of
continue with the work that you're
doing?
Well, first of all, I'd say that if you
want to use your code and you have any
questions, I think we would be happy to
to answer these questions and u we are
happy if the code is useful beyond of
course the use case we are considering.
Robotics being one one remarkable
example I think and where do we see this
placed? I think we prepared this slide
that summarizes and maybe captures on
some of the points that were discussed
and about the interdisciplinary link. Uh
so we see this uh placed in the context
of feedback systems. So in the end the
agent and the environment are two
systems that are in feedback. So this
the actions affect state and state
affect the actions.
Um and uh sorry and basically what we
did was to bring some control
theoretical and optimization methods
into this minimization of variational
free energy. So it is really an
intersection between computation
embodiment of agents and
robustness. Uh possible I think very
cool research ideas could be uh
integrating deep reinforcement learning.
So the the techniques that we the
technique that we presented Dr. three is
not mutually excluding with deep
reinforcement learning. One could use
deep reinforcement learning to learn
ambiguity. One could use deep
reinforcement learning to to learn a
better cost etc. So I think there is a
sweet spot of applications that can have
a high impact um for real world
deployments by merging these two um
these two approaches. There are also
there is also another I'm not a
neuroscientist. I'm going to start with
that. But uh I think the the model has
some cognitive implications as OA just
showed uh it supports baian belief
updates. But one thing that we had no
time to discuss about of course is that
something very nice happens in the
regimes of large and small
ambiguities. So basically when ambiguity
is small, you get the behavior of an
agent that knows everything about its
model. And it turns out that nobody
cannot perform this agent. So it's the
best possible agent. It is an oracle
essentially that does the best possible
actions will achieve the best cost
function. On the other side of the
spectrum is that when ambiguity is very
high there is a sort of a transition
where we can show it is shown in the in
the preprint that the optimal policy is
training independence in the sense that
is independent on the training model. So
it is a kind of situation where the
agent dominated by ambiguity grounds its
decisions just on ambiguity and not on
what it learned previously which is I
think it's a kind of cool behavior. Of
course I'm not a neuroscientist but I
think it's something that could be
investigated uh on on that side on that
spectrum on that side of the
spectrum. I hope I answered your
question.
Yeah, that's an interesting point. Kind
of like neuroplasticity and
age and uh how you never do worse by
knowing more about the environment, all
things being equal. And then as you turn
up the dial on ambiguity, it
erases whatever
understanding was made ambiguous.
Yeah. and and and that could be even
empirically fit to understand like what
are the biological contexts that
different
ambiguities different
hyperparameters are in play.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. Well, thank
you both and to Carl for joining. We
really appreciate the work and for for
sharing it and having to open source
code. It's really cool.
Thank you. Uh I put here two links to
the papers in and the code uh QR codes
in case you want to you are curious and
you want to check them out. And thank
you again Daniel for organizing this.
Awesome. Okay, till next time. Bye bye.
Bye.